My name's Journey.
I'm a documentary filmmaker
and sometimes I wish I were dead,
but more on that in a minute.
I'm deeply concerned
by the war on science in our culture
today.
Whether we're talking about the climate
crisis,
global pandemics,
or the mysteries of our own brains,
science is integral
to finding meaningful solutions.
And so is talking to each other.
Sometimes,
growing up American has made me feel like
I'm at a giant
family holiday where both parents hate
each other.
The family dog has died and the house is
on fire
and it's got roaches and the plumbing is
bad.
I wish we knew how to talk to each other.
Sadly, like millions of other people, I
also struggle
with depression. To be frank,
I can get really depressed...
and while it's easy to point to the
environment,
the way we treat each other, the fact
that everyone we love will die, YouTube
ads,
and meetings that could have been emails,
the truth is, I often feel blue on good
days too.
You can lose 30 pounds, quit drinking,
quit smoking,
make an effort to go outside more, eat
healthier,
basically do everything right
and still be super f*****g depressed.
With all of this in mind,
I have seriously considered taking
antidepressants, although I am hesitant.
I know people who've been really helped
by meds
and others who have killed themselves
after getting on a new antidepressant.
Studies show, in some cases, taking
antidepressants can
actually increase the risk of suicide.
Obviously, I wanted to know more before
making a decision.
So, I started reading about how these
drugs are tested
for safety, which led me
to a paper on NIH'S website explaining
that a common antidepressant testing
method
is something called "the forced swim
test."
Apparently, this test involves putting a
mouse
or a rat into a cylinder of water
that they can't escape from and timing
how long it takes
before they stop swimming.
This is supposed to simulate depression
in humans?
Another rodent is then injected with the
antidepressant
and forced to swim to see if they'll swim
for longer.
Does this mean antidepressants will make
me a better swimmer
or hate my life less?
I also realize these aren't even safety
tests.
These tests are to see if the drugs are
effective.
The idea that the swimming ability of a
rat has anything
to do with my depression seemed pretty
ridiculous.
I couldn't imagine researchers testing
antidepressants
with a human swim test.
Over 280 million people
around the world suffer from depression.
For myself, I know that this can be a
devastating,
joy-robbing, even life-threatening
illness.
The total impact of mental illness on a
person's life is
difficult to measure, but the outcomes
are clear enough.
Suicide is a leading cause of death among
young people,
and those with severe mental health
problems can die decades
early from preventable physical
conditions.
It's hard to stay healthy
and hopeful when you feel neither. People
are suffering
and dying, and yet
what seemed like an absurd testing method
was being used.
But I'm not a scientist, so I wanted to
speak
with actual researchers
to see if I could understand this better.
I reached out to the lead authors on a
number
of antidepressant papers
to get their insights on this method.
I knew I could go down a Google rabbit
hole with all
of my questions, but that's also
what my flat-earther uncle does.
I wanted to talk to actual scientists
and get a better understanding of what's
going on.
I was able to sit down with Dr.
Neal Barnard, a leading researcher
and president of the Physicians Committee
for Responsible Medicine.
The forced swim test emerged in the 1970s
because researchers were trying to find
some way to
quantify depression.
So, rather than have people just describe
their low moods,
you could put a number to it.
Rats or mice are put into a tank of water.
They can't escape, they can't get out.
They're gonna struggle and eventually
they're gonna just
give up and stop struggling.
And this is all quantified with a
stopwatch,
but it's been discredited.
It really does not apply to the depression
that a person would feel, but to this day,
it is unfortunately used
to compare antidepressants, one versus
another
or an antidepressant versus a placebo.
The forced swim test isn't done
because it's really like human depression.
It's done because you can get a number
and experimenters love numbers.
I love science, but what I just heard,
it didn't sound very scientific.
It sounded alarmingly unscientific.
It sounded like my cousin Barney threw a
rat in the pool,
set his stopwatch and called it science.
I also recognize that using animals in
research
and testing is super controversial.
A Pew Research Center survey from 2018
found that 47%
of Americans favor the practice while 52%
oppose it.
Not unlike the divide between fans of
country music
and everyone else. I myself like animals
and don't want to harm them,
but I also like the idea
of people getting life-saving medications.
I really wanted greater clarity on this
antidepressant
question before I pulled the trigger.
But the study authors still weren't
responding.
The whole thing left me wondering,
how do we know drugs are safe?
I know I'm not the first one
to ask this question: from the people who
refuse vaccination
to those who have gotten all of their
booster shots,
no one seems to have complete faith in
Big Pharma's loving,
humanitarian mission.
So, how are drugs even developed?
I went to speak with premier researcher,
biochemist
and science policy expert, Dr.
Charu Chandrasekera.
In order to bring a drug to market, we
have to go
through a long process that takes decades
of time
and costs billions of dollars.
First, you have to study the molecular
basis of disease,
and this is what's known as biomedical
research.
And this could take decades just to
understand the simple
molecule in the cell, how
that interacts with everything else.
Then you go through the drug development
process,
figuring out what kind of compounds
and selecting it down from like 10,000
compounds to maybe 10.
Then you go through animal testing,
what's known
as preclinical testing,
and then you proceed to human clinical
trials.
And after that, if they pass the clinical
trials,
you go into regulatory approval process
where you would submit your application
for a new drug
to agencies like the Food
and Drug Administration and Health Canada.
The federal government does require
that animal safety tests be done
and it's typically in a rodent species
and a non-rodent species like a dog or a
monkey.
A drug is not allowed to be on the market
unless it goes through those.
I assume drugs are required to be tested
on animals
to ensure that they're safe.
But then I found out that over 14,000 FDA
approved drugs
have been recalled in the last 10 years,
which is a level
of failure not otherwise seen outside of
my Tinder profile.
And a 2017 study
of drugs approved within a 10 year period
found
that the FDA announced alerts, warnings,
or recalls on about one third of them.
I reached out to the FDA for an interview
to find out
what the hell any of this means, but they
declined.
They did answer a few of my questions via
email.
One major part that stood out to me was
that the FDA doesn't usually test drug
safety themselves.
Instead, they rely on the drug companies
to submit accurate data for review.
And that makes sense to me because I,
too, used to take drugs
my associates had already tested for me.
I was able to sit down with Dr.
Aysha Akhtar, public health specialist
and neuroscientist with a decade of
experience at the FDA.
A recent major analysis just was
published that showed
that adverse events from drugs is the
fourth leading cause
of death in the United States.
I'm sorry, I did not know that. It's the
fourth,
the fourth leading cause of death in the,
you mean, like, up there with, like,
heart disease?
The fourth leading cause of death.
Now that's, that's ridiculous.
We can prevent that
by using more human-relevant testing
methods, methods
that will more reliably tell us whether
or not a drug is going to be safe in
humans.
I struggled to believe what I was hearing,
but sure enough, the study was right
there on
the FDA's own website.
Dr. Thomas Hartung
of Johns Hopkins University only added to
my shock
Drug interactions and drug side effects
are
actually a quite severe problem.
More than 100,000 patients which goes in
the hospital
dies from the consequences of the drug
treatments.
So this is really quite a number
and I think that a lot
of this is still not even noticed and
discovered
because very often we attribute these
things to the disease
and we don't have control over the
the side effects of drugs.
Could the regulations in place
to ensure drug safety be an ineffective
formality
like an apology from the Vatican?
I spoke with drug development policy
experts
to get a better understanding.
When companies put drugs into a clinical trial
or out onto the market, that is still an
experiment
because we don't have human relevant
preclinical
tests that are telling us
what the potential adverse reactions
might be.
It's very common for a new drug
after a few years on the market, the
packaging is revised.
So there needs to be a black box warning
that says, oops,
we realize that this causes some
major heart problem in people.
We did not anticipate this from all of
the studies
that we did using hundreds of thousands
of animals over a decade.
The current system that relies on animal
testing information
doesn't give us the full truth.
I don't think many people have a sense
of pure confidence in the decision making
that drug companies and government
agencies do.
A great example of that is Vioxx, a drug
that started causing people to have heart
attacks.
And only after that happened
and the drug was pulled, did we find out
that the maker
of the drug had tweaked its preclinical
animal data in order
just to grease the tracks and get its
drug to market.
Vioxx was safe
and effective in multiple animal models,
including a primate model, but it killed
many thousands
and thousands plus plus plus people
around the globe.
95% of all new drugs that pass
through animal tests,
once they reach human clinical trials,
they fail.
Okay, not exactly, but this is very close
to how I feel.
If this is true, that's absolutely
ludicrous.
95%? 95%?! Is all
of medicine developed with a forced swim
test?
Maybe the best treatment for my
depression is
to just stop asking questions.
Indeed, biophysicist Dr. Francis Cheng
points out
that it actually gets worse.
95%, that's the average. In cancer.
that's 96.6 of the time. In Alzheimer's,
99.6 of the time.
HIV vaccine, stroke, sepsis... a hundred
percent of the time.
And that's all failure - like, a hundred
percent
of the time failure, like, you can't get
worse than that.
So think about it like this:
It's like a plane manufacturer saying, oh
yeah, yeah,
we know our plane's gonna crash more than
nine out
of ten times, but we believe
that the model we've created is the best
there is,
and we're gonna continue to put money
and research into keeping this design.
So just hop back on the plane and trust
us.
And that's what's happening
with our drug development system.
We know the incredible high failure rate
with animal testing
and it continues
because most people aren't even aware of
it.
I wasn't aware of this anymore than most
people are aware
of the proper use of a turn signal.
But to hear scientists speak so critically
of animal testing was unnerving.
Since antiquity, animals have been at the
center
of our research into anatomy, medicine,
and biology. Public vivisection
of a pig in ancient Rome was used to
demonstrate
that vocal cords control the making of
sounds.
In medieval Spain,
new surgical techniques were tested first
on animals,
and in the 1600s,
René Descartes famously vivisected dogs
in public to show
that animals are incapable of suffering.
In the 20th century,
numerous breakthroughs in medicine came
about from using
animals as subjects for research and
testing.
We've all heard the glories of animal
research,
the discovery of insulin, penicillin, and
the polio,
vaccine - history altering medical
breakthroughs
that were possible with animals at that
time.
But these successes don't tell us how good
or bad our method has been.
These are glorified
and we hardly ever look at the failures
associated with animal models.
So if it's about human disease, we should
not expect
that an animal which just lives
for two years is representing us.
We are not 70 kilogram rats.
And then you have the other side of the
story
where you may have a drug
that presents adverse effects in an
animal model,
but it could be perfectly safe in humans.
We know, for example, that penicillin,
which is an important life-saving drug,
is lethal to Guinea pigs
and we know that aspirin is toxic to dogs.
So if those medications had been tested
first on those
species, someone might have said, ah,
maybe we shelve this and don't develop it
further.
Aspirin would fail today
almost every toxicological test you can
imagine.
It is an eye irritant, a lung irritant,
a skin irritant, producing reproductive
toxicity,
so, embryonic malformations in almost all
animal species.
We have data on mice, rats, rabbits,
cats, dogs,
monkeys, but not in humans.
There have been studies of 89,000
pregnancies in humans.
Aspirin has no such effects.
It is absolutely possible
that we have some amazing, history
altering breakthroughs,
history altering medications locked away
in some cabinet at
some pharmaceutical company.
Had I wandered into an episode of the
Twilight Zone
and not noticed? Maybe there's already a
cure for depression
that's just been overlooked
and locked away somewhere, like Barney's
wallet
every time we go to lunch.
I wanted to talk to someone who actually
works
for a pharmaceutical company.
I'm Faraz Harsini and I'm a biomedical
scientist.
I oversee and conduct projects involving
anything from drug
discovery, from R&amp;D stages
and taking them through preclinical AKA
animal studies
and phase 1, 2, 3 of clinical trials all
the way to
commercialization of the drugs.
Animal testing provides a legal sanctuary
for pharmaceutical companies.
So for us, if we test it on mice
and then go take our drug to phase one
and kill people, we can always say, oh,
hey,
it worked in mice, right?
So it's a legal protection
and a matter of liability for for us.
I can tell you that a lot of times we
don't want to do it,
and I say that on behalf
of my colleagues in pharmaceutical
companies.
I can give you a clear example:
So we had a drug
and we went with the bare minimum number
of animals we had
to test with, which was already like over
50 animals.
And then we submitted our package to FDA.
It came back
with a remark from psychologists without
any really
background in clinical research who
wanted us
to increase the number, which made it
over 200 animals.
It was crazy. And I remember we had 10
scientists in the
room and everyone was just like losing
their mind
because patients who were going to get
this drug sooner,
now they have to get it almost over a
year later.
And most importantly, some of us were
just like frustrated
because it was bad science.
It just made no sense.
What FDA wanted us to do was to design a
mouse version
of this molecule, test it against the
of the target of this drug...
So a completely irrelevant drug targeted
against a
completely irrelevant target in mouse so
that we can extrapolate from that,
that this human version is going to work
on a human target.
While we had an example of this already
in clinical trials
in humans showing that it was safe. No
one was happy.
The fact that the FDA is forcing
scientists
to develop drugs for rodents when the
actual target is
humans seemed kind of like testing a
car's safety features
by crashing bicycles.
The federal government spends tens of
billions
of dollars funding disease research every
year.
Surely they're doing a better job than
this.
Our government's doing a poor job at
finding the
treatments and cures we need
because they're still so wedded to using
animals.
So if you think about it, a hundred years
ago,
researchers used animals because that's
what they knew.
And at the time, we were looking at very
unsubtle aspects
of human biology and human anatomy.
So yeah, how a cat's heart pumps is akin
to
how a human heart pumps, for example.
But we're so well beyond that now,
we're looking at the subtle nuances of
molecular biology
and genetic expression now.
Advocates of animal testing always say
that, oh, look how
similar our DNA is.
But I think when it comes to testing on
animals
and understanding what happens in humans,
you have
to actually focus on our differences
because that can be vital in translating
the science to humans
and if you get that wrong,
you can kill people from the other side.
You know, they say like you are 85%
similar to
mice in terms of DNA.
That's not a good number. That's terrible.
We share our DNA, 44%, with bananas,
but you are not 44% bananas.
You have to think about how different we
are
because that's what makes us unique.
Although Dr. Harsini's insights made
sense to me,
I know several doctors who have insisted
that I am at least 40% bananas.
But I didn't come here to argue with
learned people.
Nearly everyone I'd spoken to
so far had participated in animal testing
and research at some point in their
career.
The message I was getting wasn't
that animal models are useless
or that they haven't taken as far,
but rather that the vehicle
for discovery we have in animals has
come with some flat tires.
Dr. Alka Chandna,
a laboratory investigator, drove the
point home.
There have been more than 100 drugs
that have reversed the debilitating
impacts
of stroke in monkeys.
And not one of those drugs helped human
patients.
You know, you go down the line
and you see that our tax dollars are
basically finding cures
for animals, which is awesome if people,
you know,
need a treatment for a monkey who's had a
stroke.
But that's not what the American
taxpayers are paying for.
They're paying for cures and treatments
for human patients,
and none of those cures
and treatments that are being developed
in animals
and laboratories are actually making it
out
to human beings. And that's a problem.
As deputy director of the Army's
Traumatic Brain Injury
Program, I was responsible for helping
to create the preventative, the diagnostic
and treatment strategies for soldiers
with traumatic brain injury.
At least five decades
of creating head injury in animals in the
labs has not led
to any effective treatment for head
injury in humans.
There are what we call supportive care,
like medications
and things to help with some of the
symptoms
that result from head injury,
but nothing to treat the head injury
itself.
And you can imagine how much the animals
suffer in labs.
They're getting their heads bashed in,
basically.
I've witnessed experiments in cats, like
my Nessie here, in
which their heads were crushed
and their spinal cords were crushed
and their legs paralyzed.
And you can see the suffering that
they've had
to endure - all for what?
All for no treatment for head injury in
humans.
Looking at a cat
to understand what's going on in the
brains of human beings,
or looking at a rat or a mouse
or a monkey to understand what's going on
in the human system.
It's like looking at a map of Australia
to figure out how
to get from San Francisco to Washington,
DC. Sure,
it's a map. It's the wrong map.
I was doing experiments on rats trying to
look at
the relationship between a high fat diet
to heart failure.
Now, in humans, we know that a high fat
diet is no good
for heart failure, but in rats,
interestingly,
that's the opposite.
When we fed the rats a high fat diet
compared
to a normal chow, they performed better
in terms
of their heart functions.
Mice and rats, they don't have this
protein called
Cholesteryl Ester Transfer Protein, which
basically shuffles
between LDL and HDL,
the bad cholesterol and the good
cholesterol.
It's known that mice and rats don't have
this protein.
So when they eat high fat diet, they're
perfectly fine,
which is not what happens in humans.
It's the complete opposite of humans.
There's tons of differences between, you
know, mice and rats
and humans in terms of heart failure
physiology,
and pathophysiology.
I never thought I'd be envious of a rat,
but if unlimited high fat foods benefited
my heart,
I probably wouldn't even have depression.
However, the differences between us
and other animals can be extremely
serious.
So when people know that I research
cancer, a lot of time,
like, okay, fine, when are we gonna get
the cure finally for, for cancer?
And I say, well, we already cured cancer
in mice
many times. It just doesn't translate to
humans
because we keep wasting time by looking
at wrong models.
The saying that, uh, "we cured cancer
in rats long ago," uh, is cynical
and, uh, certainly correct.
We have, essentially, for each
and every disease, successful molecules
which passed
their respective animal tests.
We take animals which are devoid of an
immune system
that we can graft them with human cancers.
But that's not how a cancer develops. In
cancer.
everything is about the immune system.
Unfortunately, we are no closer to any
cure
for Alzheimer's, no closer to any cure
for Parkinson's disease, no closer to any
cure
for traumatic brain injury, no closer to
any cure
for breast cancer, no closer to any cure
for pancreatic cancer.
We're no closer to any cure for most
of the diseases that afflict us.
In fact, for most human diseases out
there,
there's no treatment, no drug
or vaccine that's been approved
whatsoever.
So we are really behind, I would say -
farther behind
than we should be at this point in
finding the treatments
and the cures we need.
Cancer is the second leading cause of
death in the USA.
My grandmother, my aunt, my cousin,
and several of my friend's parents have
all been taken by cancer.
I know the disease itself can be hell,
but what I've personally seen most
of all is the devastation
it leaves behind. The grief.
The people shaped holes in our lives.
I don't know anyone who hasn't in some way
been affected by cancer.
The idea that we haven't been been
fighting these diseases
as efficiently as possible is extremely
upsetting.
Every time you have one of these medical
research charities collecting money from
the public
to fund the next great cure
or advertise that there's a cure around
the corner
for cancer or diabetes
or Alzheimer's, there are some ethics
involved with that
because there are no cures around the
corner
because most of that money goes into
animal research.
We as scientists
and as a society, need
to think about the ethics of human hope.
As long as they are continuing to put
money
into methods like animal testing that
have been proven again
and again, not to work, not to be
effective, not
to be reliable, then they're really being
disingenuous to the public.
They need to come forward.
They need to come clean about what
they're doing
and how like animal testing is not
leading to treatments,
despite of what they tell people.
You are utilizing the vulnerability of
the human patients.
You're getting their money
and then you're not doing a good job
and you're not getting anything in return
for them. It's just not right.
Oftentimes I think about all these
marathons
that people have, and anytime I see
people running
for the cure, I almost wanna go and stop
them
and tell them, you're not running for a
cure.
You are running from a cure
because you don't even know where this
money is going,
and if it's going to fund more and more
and more animal research,
you will never get the cure that you are
looking for.
I didn't want to believe these harsh
criticisms
of beloved medical charities
and none of what I was hearing was helping
with my depression, particularly when
thinking
of organizations like the American Heart
Association.
Heart disease is the number one cause
of death in the United States.
My father, one of the most important
people in my life,
suffered a major cardiac event and nearly
died.
I am incredibly grateful for the drugs
that were available
to help save his life.
I reached out to some of the bigger
charities
to see if they would comment on the harsh
criticisms I was
hearing, but they either declined an
interview
or didn't reply altogether.
In the case of the American Cancer
Society, I asked
for a list of successful drugs
that came from research they funded,
but their vice president of marketing
strategy wrote back
to say that as far as she knew, no such
list exists.
I was still concerned that the picture
of animal testing I was getting might be
more lopsided than
my youth pastor's take on evolution.
I was having a hell of a time finding
anyone
who would use their expertise to speak to
the merits
of animal testing on camera.
It's so freaking frustrating.
I'm just hearing from people who are
critical
of animal testing, it's fracking
"this is wrong with animal testing"
and "this is fudging wrong with animal
testing,"
but no one who actually does the
gosh darn animal testing is gonna respond
to me
and help me help them. They're
forking saving the world
somehow, but they won't go on dag nab
camera and they're messing up my movie.
Fortunately, I was able to sit down with
Dr. Paul Locke,
a lawyer and scientist at Johns Hopkins
University.
I know there are a lot of people that'll
argue
that today we need
to move away immediately from animal
models,
but the truth of the matter is we can't
do that.
And the further truth of the matter is we
shouldn't do that.
Animal models are still the backbone of a
lot
of our research, and they still do yield
important
information, but I've never met a
scientist who uses animals
that wouldn't in a minute, in a minute
drop their animal model if something
better
that didn't use animals comes along.
However, we're not there yet.
If you're talking about today somehow
flipping a switch
and ending all animal testing,
the world would not be a good place.
It would grind our scientific research to
a halt.
I don't think it's any surprise to anyone
that animal models have limitations.
The first limitation is pretty obvious.
Animals and humans, or I should say
non-human animals
and human animals are different.
Their biology is different.
So very often what you find are things
that work,
for example, in a rodent
or even things that work in non-human
primates,
which are very close to humans, just
don't work in humans.
So we need to have testing methods
and we need to have science that's very
human centric.
Dr. Locke, who was supportive of the use
of animals in science generally, was also
open about the
limitations of this method.
His point about results in non-human
primates not
translating to humans was especially
fascinating.
I really wanted to hear from an expert
who currently works
with animals in a lab,
but the researchers I had reached out
to still weren't responding...
Hello, my name is Journey Wade-Hak.
Hi, my name's Journey Wade-Hak.
I'm making a documentary and- Hi, Journey
Wade-Hak here.
I'm calling because- I'm calling about
setting up an interview with you-
I'm doing a documentary about drug
development
and I wanted to know if you would be open
to doing an interview- and getting anyone
else to confirm
or even call me back was starting
to feel like prom, 2008, all over again.
Luckily, I was able to arrange a visit
with Chimp Haven,
a place that cares for chimpanzees
formerly used in federally funded research
and the largest chimp sanctuary in the
world.
In the late eighties and early nineties,
chimpanzees were being used for HIV and
AIDS research.
At that time, we were in that pandemic
and nobody knew a lot about those
diseases,
and so the chimpanzees were being used to
try
to develop a vaccine for both hepatitis
but also HIV.
And as it turned out, chimpanzees
actually don't develop
AIDS in the same way a human being does.
And so they didn't turn out
to actually be a really great model for
that research.
But at the time we started breeding
chimpanzees
because we thought we were gonna need them
to be utilized in this type of research
in the future.
So there ended up being a large
population of chimpanzees
and then the research sort of fell off
and funding fell off for it
because they turned out not
to be such a great model for these things.
We don't retire most animals that are
used in research.
A lot of animals are actually euthanized
and chimpanzees were one species
that everyone agreed should not be
euthanized at the end
of their time in research
and that they should actually go to some
sort of retirement.
So this was a new concept and a new idea
in terms of retiring chimpanzees. They
can live a long time.
We have a couple 63 year olds here at
Chimp Haven.
Alpha Male has arrived.
Yeah, there's varying ages in here.
Our youngest is Carlee, who's up over
there in the tree.
Carlee learned at a very young age
that if she goes up in the tree, a lot
of the adults will leave her be
so she can take her treats up there for
eating.
Me too, Carlee. Me too.
If you think about hepatitis research,
it would've been liver biopsies that were
done on them
and sometimes multiple liver
biopsies that they might have had.
Yeah, it just, their research histories
really vary
and one of the things that Chimp Haven
really wants
to concentrate on their future here
and not their past so much.
When the federal government stopped using
chimps in 2013,
they actually kept 50 on hand just
in case they might need them.
But after a couple of years, just like my
dreams
of home ownership and normal weather
conditions,
they let them go, too. I had
to wonder, if our closest living
relatives are not very
reliable stand-ins for our biology,
what did that mean for monkeys, rats,
dogs, and all the rest?
Finally, I was able to make contact
with the Texas Biomedical Research
Institute
about arranging an interview.
Their PR person told me a great fit could
be Dr.
Deepak Kaushal, the director of their
primate center.
She said he was "very open"
and "wonderful"
and that if that interview could happen,
I would need
to know that interviews are allowed,
but footage of their animals is not.
I could only assume I wasn't allowed to
film the animals
because it would be inhumane to subject
them
to my intolerable vibrations.
Still, I was excited to finally talk to
an expert
who would wholeheartedly advocate for the
merits
of animal testing. But not two weeks
later,
the very person I had hoped to interview,
the director
of their primate center, Dr.
Kaushal, was found guilty of falsifying
animal data
in published research and in federal
grant applications.
Despite all of his dishonesty, the US
Office
of Research Integrity didn't even require
that he be removed from his position.
I've known people who were fired for way
less,
like taking paperclips home from the
office.
That you could lie to the government,
take their money
and still keep your federally funded job
at the head
of a $40 million
Primate Institute is a level of impunity
usually reserved
for police and politicians.
Only after significant public outrage was
he demoted a month
later. Not fired. Still on staff
and still taking federal money.
For some reason, they stopped responding
to my emails.
But I found out that this sort of
misconduct, like a senator
with a stock portfolio, is not
as isolated as I would've hoped.
Data manipulation in the form
of omission is a much more common
practice, often referred
to as publication bias.
There was a big example of publication
bias in
hormone replacement therapy.
It's often given to women after menopause.
They've got hot flashes, they're
miserable,
they can't sleep, and if you give them
estrogens,
some of those symptoms go away.
The question was, could it also help
their heart?
And in animal studies, you could show
that hormone replacement therapy really
did
seem to be a benefit.
However, two huge trials put this
to the test in human beings. The studies
had to be stopped
because the women were having heart
attacks
as a result of the treatment.
And so researchers went back and they
said, wait,
the animal studies said this ought to be
safe.
It turned out that the animal studies
that disagreed were just being left out.
They were just not being published.
It was a massive case of publication
bias. Why?
Because nobody requires you to publish
a study if you don't like the results
if the subjects were animals. If the
subjects were animals,
you can just throw it away.
Cherry picking results,
dropping those experiments which "did not
work,"
very often leads us to research which
cannot
be reproduced by others.
Meaning that the results are not real.
The results are not true
and this is a huge issue in preclinical
testing
because it's so rampant.
What it means is that all of the money
that
we as taxpayers have spent
producing those experimental results
might be wasted.
Major pharmaceutical companies like Amgen
have found
that up to 89%
of the academic studies they base their
new drug development
on cannot be reproduced... much like the
golden age of hip hop.
And that's only reproducibility
for studies involving the same species,
like a rat to a rat
or a dog to a dog,
and doesn't even look at the fundamental
problem
of translating those results to actual
human beings.
One area where this is particularly
worrisome is toxicology.
Toxicology testing is very important.
It's basically helping us understand the
safety
or potential toxicities of chemicals
and then making decisions about how
to protect humans and the environment.
Most of the tests that are used
for regulatory toxicology testing today
were developed 50
to 80 plus years ago.
So these are tests that have been
basically grandfathered in
as acceptable, but they were never
formally validated
for their reliability or relevance to
humans.
Well, those tests tell you
what would happen if you put a chemical
in a rabbit's eye
or what would happen if you force fed a
chemical to a rat.
They don't necessarily tell you
what would happen if humans are exposed
to that chemical.
To give you one example
here, a few years ago,
Coca-Cola was forced to change a dye in
Coke
because of an animal test where cancer
was developed
in rats. The equivalent dose we would need
to drink is 8,000 cans of Coke per day.
That's the dose at which cancer developed.
So it's a completely irrelevant finding,
and this shows how crazy the economical
consequences are
of an animal test
which is simply not properly doing the
job.
Dr. Hartung calls it a "completely
irrelevant finding,"
but apparently he doesn't remember what
it's like
to be a sugar addicted 10-year-old with a
dream.
Let's be honest, we use animals in
research every day.
The area I work mostly in, which is
toxicology policy,
right now still involves a lot of animal
testing.
But what we're seeing is
that we're bumping up against some
limits in the use of animals.
We have to evolve the tests that don't
use animals, tests
that really focus on human biology
and give us information about
how things react in human systems.
If I want to know whether the substance
is producing
cancer, the standard approach today is
to run a cancer bioassay.
This will give you results in about five
years.
You pay around $1 million for testing a
single substance.
So most stuff comes to the market
and has never been tested, whether it's
producing cancer
or not, because they don't want to wait
for five years
to get this. Time to market is most
critical.
Maybe it's naive of me to be surprised
that money would come before public
safety,
but as my mom would say, I'm not mad, I'm
just disappointed.
The FDA and EPA are supposed
to be protecting us from toxins,
but they've been fighting a losing battle
against a growing
list of unknown and untested substances
since at least the eighties.
From toxicology to basic research,
it turns out the government is a big part
of the problem.
The National Institutes of Health
actually is the largest governmental
funder of research.
About 50% of their funding goes towards
experiments
that include animal experimentation.
Right now, that's $20 billion a year going
to fund animal experiments.
Legislators on Capitol Hill often simply
blindly give NIH
whatever it asks for when it comes to
funding increases
and don't expect any real accountability.
A lot of this money goes to universities
where animal experimenters engage in
what they call "basic research."
So at the University of Wisconsin,
Madison,
there was an experimenter who was taking
cats
and he would intentionally deafen the
cats.
Then he would put metal coils near their
eyes,
cut into their heads, saw off a portion
of the skull,
implant electrodes...
He was extremely explicit.
He said, I'm not looking for a cure for
deafness.
I'm not even looking for a way
to develop better hearing aids.
I just wanna understand what parts
of the brain control sound localization.
And he got tens of millions
of dollars from the National Institutes
of Health.
I think taxpayers would be outraged to
learn that
huge portions of these grants from NIH
given to universities
and colleges aren't going towards
research.
They are going towards the construction
of new buildings.
It could be a new dining hall, it could
be new sidewalk.
They're not necessarily buildings related
to research
or healthcare or improving public health.
They could be anything because every
university gets
to take part of that grant and use it as
it sees fit.
Universities need to keep funds coming in
to keep their departments alive.
And so this is absolutely one of the
drivers
of animal use in experiments
where there is no legal requirement to
conduct these tests.
Animal testing that happens at a
university laboratory,
unless they're developing a drug being
presented to the Food
and Drug Administration or another
regulator,
that testing can end tomorrow.
It's being carried out because a
laboratory wants to do it.
There are so many studies -
there are legacy studies, studies that
were funded
for the last 28 years.
They haven't yielded anything useful for
humans,
and yet they continue to be funded.
At Wayne State University in Detroit,
there are these heart failure
and hypertension dog experiments
that have been going on since 1991.
They've received more than $15 million in
NIH money.
We reviewed all of the papers published
from these studies.
We tried to track down any new treatments
or new devices that have come from these
and we can't find anything.
We wrote to NIH a few years ago to say,
why are you still funding this?
And when they finally wrote us back, they
said,
we looked at the publications from this
research
and we believe those publications are
contributing
to an impressive body of science.
So over the course of three decades,
the only reason NIH continues to fund
these experiments is
because of the published papers, not
because of any tangible outcomes for
patients
who are suffering from heart disease,
hypertension, or heart failure.
There are people at universities who
purport
to study Parkinson's disease.
They might inject a toxin into the brain
so
that the monkeys develop a tremor.
So you're getting the symptom of
Parkinson's,
but that's not Parkinson's.
That is not what's happening in
Parkinson's patients.
These are diseases
that are developing sometimes over
decades,
but that's not what the animal
experimenters are studying.
If they were doing studies to help people
who actually have serious illnesses,
whether we're talking about cancer or
Alzheimer's disease
or others, they would be studying those
human diseases using
the state-of-the-art
research methods that we have available
now.
While today I am mature enough to
recognize
that investing in Toys R Us
and Blockbuster was a mistake on my part,
the fact
that we continue to invest billions of
dollars into research
that isn't applicable
to human beings is blowing my mind. How
does this happen?
Unfortunately, animal research is big
business
because we're not just talking about the
animals
used in the lab.
So there are major corporations
that import, like, non-human primates
into the United States.
There are major companies that breed dogs
and other animals to be used in
experiments.
Companies that create the cages, companies
that create the restraining devices that
are used
to restrain these animals when they're
being experimented on,
companies that produce the food.
A little black mouse could cost up
to 30 US dollars. If you want a
diabetic rat, it's around 500 US dollars
to purchase from a company.
And all these little instruments,
can you think about having a little
catheter that needs
to go into a mouse heart?
Well, those cost thousands of dollars.
Everything in animal research is
extremely expensive.
And so you can imagine there's a lot of
business
and corporate entities that want to hold
on
to animal experimentation
because that's how they make their money.
If you go to any public meeting
that a government agency holds about a
non-animal test
method is being considered
as a replacement for an animal method...
Representatives from contract research
organizations attend,
and they also bring attorneys with the
express purpose
of making sure
and keeping a given animal test in place
that that's preserved.
I wish I had this sort of lobbying power
for my own financial interests.
Industry influencing policy is an old
story,
but we don't always get to see everyone
that they impact.
So this is Samson. Samson is an
8-year-old male beagle.
He was rescued 11 days ago from a
5,000 dog breeding mill in the United
States
that raises beagles
and sells them to laboratories for use in
experiments.
They sell them to the National Institutes
of Health.
They sell them to universities,
and they sell them to contract research
organizations
that experiment on these animals.
Samson was born at this facility
and until 10 days ago, he'd never seen a
bed.
He'd probably never put his paws on grass,
largely been housed alone for all eight
years
of his so-called life to that point.
So Samson was primarily a breeding
animal.
And the records at this facility where he
was kept show
his breeding produced, so to speak, about
200 puppies.
Those animals are each sold for hundreds
and hundreds of dollars, if not more.
And so over the course of his eight years,
he made this company likely a hundred
thousand dollars.
After spending some time with Samson,
I wondered if the sale of his puppies
to laboratories made enough money
for everyone involved to sleep at night.
With so much money going into animal
research
and testing, I knew to look
for lobbying power coming out of it.
It turns out that this industry is so
powerful,
it can actually shape laws.
That's when I learned about the Animal
Enterprise Terrorism Act.
Delci Winders, a legal scholar
with expertise in this area, explained.
The Animal Enterprise Terrorism Act is a
law designed to
protect animal using industries,
including the biomedical research
industry,
and to put enhanced criminal penalties on
anybody
who is doing anything to interfere with
research facility
or other covered facility.
It was designed to be very broad
and to reach First Amendment activities
and
the Center for Constitutional Rights has
said that,
the ACLU has weighed in.
This was the result of legislative efforts
by industry interests
to basically criminalize their opponents.
Consider the case of "Stop Huntington
Animal
Cruelty," or SHAC.
To make a long story short,
some disturbing undercover footage
came out of the laboratories at
Huntington Life Sciences
or HLS, a multinational corporation
that tests other companies' products on
animals.
In response, a campaign, SHAC, was mounted
to get other businesses to divest from
HLS.
In 2004, Andy Stepanian, a SHAC activist,
was arrested
and charged with conspiring
to violate the law's precursor, the Animal
Enterprise Protection Act,
even though his activism was textbook
First Amendment activity.
They were arguing that we caused upwards
of $15 million worth of financial losses
to the laboratory
through our protest campaign.
We couldn't argue that part.
I couldn't argue the part that I didn't
travel across state lines.
I did. I couldn't argue the part
that I organized protests - I did. I
couldn't argue the part
that I "utilized facilities in foreign
and interstate commerce," in this case,
the internet.
I did. I did all of those things,
but all of those things were a
conglomerate
of legal activities.
And that collection
of legal activities somehow found me
guilty of
a federal conspiracy charge
to which I served three years in federal
prison.
Despite being a model prisoner in a
medium security
facility, for the last six months of his
sentence,
Andy was labeled something called a
"prisoner
of inspirational significance"
and moved into a maximum security prison
where he served the rest of his time in a
Communications
Management Unit designed for people
considered
to have the most violent and egregious
offenses.
In other words, Andy went exactly where
my Uncle Dave
says protestors belong.
I had one simple and self-interested
question:
Has anything changed in the last 20 years
in terms
of like, can this happen again if someone
were
to launch a similar campaign
or I, I'm - even making this film
that's turning out rather critical of
these industries?
The laws themselves haven't changed.
So I think it's right to be wary. It's
still risky.
I won't say that you will be criminalized
for making this film, but I'll say
that we are living in a moment in history
where it's becoming increasingly easy for
industry
to create designer statutes
that would criminalize this film.
A year earlier, I was depressed
and conflicted about taking meds for it.
I had no idea that making a documentary,
exploring my questions around
that could ever, in a million years,
violate an
anti-terrorism statute.
I knew this was a big industry
and that there would be pushback for
making a critical film,
but it really hit home
after talking to Andy Stepanian -
these forces put him in prison.
So I decided to call my co-producer,
Keegan Kuhn, someone
who had been down this path before, to
hear what he thinks.
I'm starting to get really worried,
actually,
about making this film
and I wanted to ask, based on your
experience,
what kind of stuff should I
expect?
You can expect death threats, blackball
websites,
media attacks, character attacks,
surveillance, potential
even lawsuits to try
and discredit the film, to try and
bankrupt the film,
And honestly, this industry has
incredible power,
and they're gonna use all of their tools
to try and scare you into silence.
Look, they've- they put people in
prison for exposing far less.
Talking to Keegan had not exactly been
soothing.
My hair started falling out in patches
again,
which happens when I'm stressed.
But despite the dangers of making this
film, I was surprised
by my own lack of lasting fear.
Maybe it was my depression robbing me of
rational thinking,
but I quickly found myself feeling far
more determined
to find answers than afraid of reprisals.
I knew there were other arguments about
the science
of using animals and that it was important
to hear them from people
who weren't actively involved in a
scandal.
Thankfully, I finally did hear back from
a group called
Americans for Medical Progress.
So why are animal models of research
important for human wellbeing?
Let me make this very simple for you.
Virtually every single medical
convenience you can think of,
every medication you can take for
anything,
and there are thousands of medications
available
for all kinds of ailments, every vaccine,
so every preventive, every diagnostic,
you know, all
of these imaging techniques, every
surgical intervention,
every single medical convenience you can
think of that
has allowed us all to live 20,
or more, you know, 30 more years to have
this conversation
has started with research in animals.
I have personally witnessed animal studies
that resulted in new cancer therapies
that literally save lives.
When I was at Oregon Health
and Science University, we developed a
drug named Gleevec,
which was used to treat leukemia patients.
And these were patients
who were literally planning their
funerals.
And those patients are still alive
today thanks to that drug.
I've also witnessed an immunotherapy drug
that was created at an institution where
I used
to work. Another case
where people were literally planning
their funerals
and are alive today.
And those studies, once again, came
from animals in research.
Some people say that 95% of drugs that
passed
through animal testing go on
to fail in human clinical
trials. Would you comment on that?
This statement, this 95% works in animals
and doesn't work in people is a-
is a complete misrepresentation of the
process, right?
It makes people think, well,
these things cure disease in animals
and they don't cure disease in people,
and
in many cases it has nothing to do with
that.
It's frequently used by animal rights
groups.
What's really interesting is actually if
you go back
and look at the NIH website, that website
makes no mention
of animal studies whatsoever.
And the reason is because the process
of developing a new therapy
or a new medication involves a tremendous
number of methodologies.
And at the end of that entire process,
you have a medication
that either is - gets through
the approval process or does not.
And that's approximately 5% right now.
And, and that's, that's essentially how
science works.
There are are a million reasons why a drug
does not make it through all the process
and it's really unfortunate
that animal rights groups are claiming
that animals are the problem.
And so the use of this 95% figure is
actually
pretty fictional.
Of course, there was another question on
my mind.
I was curious if you could comment on
where Americans
for Medical progress gets most of its
funding.
Oh, sure, sure. Uh,
so our organization gets funding from a,
a wide variety of sources.
Um, some of it comes from universities,
some
of it comes from re- uh, companies
that develop medications, et cetera.
A lot of it also comes from, from just
citizens that,
that donate dollars because they believe
in our mission.
For someone like me, who is not a
scientist, hearing PhDs
with years of experience doing research
on animals,
give different takes on the meaning
of this 95% number can feel sort
of like looking at esoteric dials
that I would never understand.
So I reached out to Don Ingber, a Harvard
professor
and pioneer in the world of biomedical
research
to see if he could add some clarity.
Yeah, I mean, I've seen ranges from 70%
to 95% of drugs failing when they get to
the clinic.
And there are many reasons for that,
and it's not all animal testing based.
Sometimes it's clinical trial design
based,
but even if it's 70, I often say in my
lectures
to graduate students, if your professor
were to tell you
to design your next experiment based on
your failures, you'd laugh.
But that's the way the multi-trillion
dollar
pharmaceutical industry basically works.
It's sort of failure, failure, failure,
and they keep going.
And I do think we could do a lot better
than that.
There are examples, like liver toxicity,
where we know the results in animals are
totally different than humans.
So the exact number is sort
of less important than the reality that
there is no one
that I have met in the pharmaceutical
industry, biotech, FDA
or any regulatory agency around the world
who doesn't admit
that the animal models are suboptimal
and there needs to be a better way.
While I could hear the argument that
animal models
of research were still necessary in some
cases,
the enormous power
and waste I had been learning about made
me think the
problem wasn't solely a technical one.
Excessive attachment to traditional ways
of doing things can be found everywhere.
From biomedical research to cheating at
monopoly
and gaslighting your cousins,
it's all too natural to feel like there's
no other
way but what you've been taught
Throughout my career,
researchers who've been really wedded
to using animal experiments, have bullied
me,
have harassed me, have tried to get me
fired for
expressing some doubts about the use of
animal testing
for understanding human health.
And I believe they were threatened by the
idea that up
and coming researchers
and doctors are really questioning not
the elephant in the
room, but the mouse in the room.
One of the, the most profound experiences
that I had sitting at my dad's bedside
after he had a quadruple bypass surgery
and realizing
that the animal models I was creating in
the lab,
the heart failure mouse models, that they
were never going
to help people like him
or the guy who was sitting next to his bed
or everybody in that cardiac ward.
My research was never going
to make a difference for people like that.
That is not sentimental.
That's using my judgment as a scientist
to do something different.
This is how our culture evolved.
I carried out animal testing pretty much
throughout my
life, like, the bulk part of my life up
to the middle of my PhD.
That is when I started
to think "maybe this whole thing isn't
right."
All the professors, all my colleagues,
all my fellow students, they're all doing
this.
It cannot be wrong.
So I went to my committee meeting
and then one professor told me, "don't
think about it."
"Get your head down, finish your research,
publish your research and get out.
Graduate. You know, this is not something
that you should be concerned about."
Like, just, she straight up said that.
That's when I decided that I'm not going
to do this anymore.
For my thesis, in the front, there was a
line:
"For all the animals that I have killed.
I'm sorry. I was wrong." My thesis
advisor told me
that if I put that in, it will jeopardize
my chance of graduation.
But let the record show that I intended to
acknowledge the animals, um, that I've
harmed and killed.
Dr. Cheng's story reminded me
that inefficiency in the lab isn't why a
majority
of Americans disapprove of animal testing
or why some people protest the places
that do it.
What did you see that moved you so much?
During this brief period of time
that the undercover investigator was
inside the laboratory in New Jersey,
she documented horrific cruelty,
including the live necropsy
of a primate without anesthetic on a
table.
Its entire torso opened up, ribcage
opened up,
heart still beating, and the being tried
to snap
and bite the people that were cutting her
apart.
And while doing so, one of the
technicians said something
to the extent of, "you wanna f***in' bite
me?"
"Let's dance, b***h! Let's dance!"
And was chastising
and like making fun of this animal
that they were cutting apart alive.
And I just saw that and I'm like, how
does this exist?
And so they say that we're extreme, right?
My actions, dubbed extremism, pale in
comparison
to cutting apart a creature on a table,
making fun of it
as you take its life from them, without
anesthetic,
as it convulses on this table.
The dogs repeatedly getting punched in
the face.
These are not isolated incidents when you
have a laboratory
in Occold, England where there's a hidden
camera going
and a laboratory in East Millstone, New
Jersey
where a camera's going,
and for the brief period of time
that those reporters were in there,
couple of weeks here
and a couple of weeks there, that they
get this trove
of evidence that shows this?
It doesn't show that these are outliers.
It doesn't show that there's a couple of
bad apples.
It shows that the whole orchard is rotten.
Occasionally, you'll see some really
troubling footage,
and we certainly would never say that
um, everybody involved in biomedical
research is a hundred
percent perfect a hundred percent of the
time.
There are some bad actors
and unfortunately, um, you know, when an
infiltration occurs
and they show the bad actors, um,
unfortunately
that's portrayed as being the standard
situation.
I will tell you from working in a
research setting,
I have never seen somebody mistreat an
animal in my,
you know, 15 or so years working in a
primate facility,
working in other facilities,
and it disgusts me when I, when I see an
image like that,
um, that is not the norm and nor should
it be
and certainly the laws
and regulations that exist should be used
in those cases.
Reassuring though it was to imagine
that I could work in research for over a
decade
and never witness the mistreatment of an
animal,
it didn't match with the other stories I
was hearing.
I decided to meet with Dr.
John Gluck, a psychologist who worked on
monkeys
in laboratories for most of his career
before deciding to instead study
bioethics.
I can't imagine somebody really heavily
experienced in
animal labs who could say they've never
seen anything.
I think what people probably mean when
they say
they haven't seen mistreatment is they
haven't seen,
you know, monkeys being punched
or gratuitously exposed to painful stimuli
and so on and so forth.
You'd have to have a pretty narrow
definition of
what "mistreatment" means to say
"I haven't seen it." A lot of just the
basic things that we do
to animals in laboratories are
mistreatment.
I think we're, we're fooling ourselves if
we
say we've never seen it.
So this is Gizmo. He's a long-tail
macaque.
He was used in animal experimentation. As
with all
of the monkeys who come to us from labs,
we don't know his backstory. They come to
us as this kind
of unknown. Unknown trauma has happened
to them at some stage. He
and his group all came to us with their
restraint collars on.
We can guess some of the types
of things that were done to them.
They weren't used in behavioral studies.
They were at some stage restrained, which
points
to invasive studies.
We had one monkey called Theo, who has
now passed away,
who came to us from a laboratory.
He had recurring eye problems
that we just couldn't get to the bottom
of.
We, we could tell that he was struggling
with his eyesight,
but every exam, his eyes looked perfectly
normal.
So we ended up taking him to a specialist,
and what they found was that a six inch
piece
of wire had been left in his skull.
Laboratories talk about retiring monkeys
as if they've kind
of lived this full life and had this
working life,
and then they choose to kind of give it up
to go, you know, go and live in Florida.
But they come to us and they're
traumatized.
You know, some of them have been tortured.
At the very least they've been socially
isolated,
and sanctuary isn't a happy ending.
Sanctuary is a really difficult journey
for all of them.
All of these answers brought up an
important question for me.
What is the state of laws
and regulations around cruelty in
laboratories?
I met with Deborah Press, a legal expert
and former USDA inspector.
And the Animal Welfare Act is more
remarkable for
what it doesn't do than for what it does.
Lots of cruelty is conducted by, by
plenty of Animal Welfare
Act regulated businesses. You know,
experiments forcing dogs
to run on treadmills until their hearts
give out.
So much of this is legal under the Animal
Welfare Act.
There are a lot of good inspectors at USDA
that are veterinarians that do a really
good job.
We just saw this recently where hundreds
of beagles were being bred for animal
research,
and they did an undercover investigation.
The USDA inspectors kept telling their
higher ups
that it was a terrible situation, that
they needed
to go back more, that they needed
to bring in more inspectors,
and the higher up said no, you, optics
would be bad-
The optics would be bad for saving dogs
from rampant cruelty?
Shocking, right? Who are the optics bad
for?
They're bad for the research institution.
USDA doesn't want to look like they're
doing too much.
They don't wanna look like they're
bringing down the hammer on the entities
that they regulate.
We just see time and time again,
the enforcement isn't there.
They're not gonna stand up to industry.
There has only ever been a single
criminal prosecution
of an animal experimenter in the United
States,
and that conviction was overturned
by the state Supreme Court.
I had to hope, to wonder if the kind
of cruelty being described
to me was something from a bygone era of
research.
Then I spoke to someone who was working
for a laboratory at the time of our
interview,
an interview they agreed
to only on the condition of anonymity.
What is life like for the animals in your
work?
Usually the animals are kept in crowded,
unclean conditions.
Some are bred to have debilitating
illnesses
or given purposeful injuries.
I've seen illnesses
and injuries that were unrelated
to the research be ignored, supposedly
because treatment may interfere with
results.
I've also seen animals suffer and die
because they were denied proper food,
water, or help.
I've seen animals too paralyzed to drag
themselves to food.
Some with ulcerated eyes
or weeping skin wounds, prolapsed organs.
It has been traumatic to witness.
I wanted to explore the science
behind the medicines we take.
I really did not want to look at what
happens to the animals
inside of these places, but
with everything I was learning, how could
I not look?
The physical brutality, the cruelty is
hard to look at.
It is ugly and it is nauseating.
For me, there is a greater, existential
nausea
that comes not from looking at the
technician punching a
beagle or the scientist dissecting a
primate without an anesthesia.
It's the people around them who don't
interfere,
who don't write reports, who circle the
wagons
and pull out a checkbook to make the
problem disappear
and act like we're all doing our best.
The lobbyists who write impunity into the
law
and the people like me who don't want to
look
because it is so uncomfortable to see
what is done in my name. How does this
continue?
When I was in college, we were studying
psychology.
I remember I was putting some electrodes
into the brain
of a white rat that had been given to me
by my professor,
and we had to put them in a stereotactic
device,
which is like a metal pencil
that goes into this ear and into this ear.
And as I put this rat in the stereotactic
device
and I turned the little thumbscrews at
one point I heard "thk,
thk" and I said to my professor, I said,
"I,
I think I just went through his eardrums."
And he said, "perfect. That's where you
wanna be.
That'll hold his skull really tight."
I said, "but wait a minute. You know,
doesn't that hurt?"
He said "he wasn't gonna listen to his
stereo tomorrow anyway."
This was a kind man. He was a nice guy.
But I realized that somehow his culture
of being in science made him miss the
most obvious things,
which is animals feel pain.
And frankly, there was no point to what
we were doing.
Most people, they just get desensitized
enough to carry out the work.
But then in their mind, deep down,
they're battling that oppression
because you're trying
to intentionally inflict diseases and pain
and distress in animals
and eventually killing them without
affecting your work.
So that is a constant battle
and we, we know that PTSD is a real thing
for ex animal experimenters.
And we see this in the veterinary field.
We see this in slaughterhouse workers.
Animal experimenters are not exceptions.
We are the human victims In the animal
testing world.
It's hard to find people who, who love
people
and animals so strongly
that they can actually do that for years
and years.
And so they need support. And I,
I feel very strongly about this.
I think our community has not done nearly
enough
to support them properly.
They really need to evaluate the nature
of this, uh,
you call it compassion fatigue.
I'm not crazy about that term,
but the nature of that, uh, for our folks
is not the same
as it is for an ICU nurse, you know,
who's just trying
to take care of a very sick patient
or a veterinarian who gets a very sick
animal
and has to put the animal down.
You know, our people are sometimes tasked
with
euthanizing animals who are, you know,
for the most part
healthy, because the study's over.
These are animals they cared for directly
that they then have to euthanize.
And it's been likened to something that's
more similar to
what, um, war veterans would go through,
right?
You know, they're, they're in
a situation where they know they're doing
the right thing.
They're defending their country and you
know,
in this, in this example, right?
But maybe they have to kill women and
children
because the circumstances become very
dangerous
and dictate that. They have to...
That's not the- it's a very different
kind of struggle.
What the f**k? Do we have to kill women
and children?
Is that necessary? And I don't, I mean,
I expected to hear that kind of
comparison from someone
who works for PETA, not from someone
who's an advocate
for doing research on animals.
Is the fight against disease like a war?
And is it good for scientists to see
themselves as soldiers?
When a student in our lab says, "I'm
squeamish about what you're asking me to
do to these animals
as part of my experiment," what are we
likely to say?
"Well, maybe you're not built for this
profession."
So maybe you're just too wimpy
to deal with the truth.
In other words, shut up.
So that's what we're telling those people
when we tell them
that their concerns
or their sensitivities are irrelevant,
we're saying just toughen up.
Just like being in bootcamp. The model of
I'm a soldier
just doesn't work for me.
I know something about being insensitive,
dismissive,
and attached to an old way of thinking.
Until I got older and saw more of the
world,
I thought Great Britain was a myth used
to scare children.
Nevertheless, even though I could
appreciate
that animal research and testing
in best case scenarios still yields
useful information,
it was increasingly clear
that this system isn't meaningfully
regulated,
that it abides unbelievable cruelty above
and beyond the already upsetting
experiments
and that an unconscionable amount
of the experimentation going on with
animals today
doesn't fit into that category of
lifesaving and necessary.
Over the course of these interviews,
I had heard about alternatives
to animal experiments like computer
processing,
cell cultures, non-invasive imaging,
and 3D bioprinting human tissue.
One of the most impressive new
alternatives is called an
"organ on a chip," which sounded like a
cross
between something from Star Trek and an
hors d'oeuvre.
So I visited Emulate, a company in Boston
that develops them, to learn more.
An organ on a chip is a small device that
allows you
to culture human cells.
So these are usually taken from a biopsy
of a patient
and it allows these cells to grow in
and form tissues like they do in the body.
And so that's relevant
because alternatives, using animal tissues
or using systems that don't provide flow
or stretching, they're, they're lacking a
lot of
that physiologic relevance.
And so you're able to test any drug that
you want
to introduce into the system and also
different cell types.
We just published a large study in a
nature portfolio
journal called Communications Medicine,
and in this study we tested 27 different
compounds on our liver chip
to see if they cause drug induced liver
injury.
These were a known set of compounds that
had gone
through animal in vivo testing,
had gone into human clinical trials.
So we had animal data and human data.
Of those drugs, 22 of them were deemed
hepatotoxic
by the FDA classification.
All 22 of those were missed by animals
and went into clinical trials.
Our liver chip was able to detect 87% of
those
that were missed by animals.
Looking at the history of these drugs, um,
of the 22, 2 were stopped in clinical
trials
because of patient fatalities.
Patients unfortunately passed away.
10 of them ended up making it to market
and then being pulled off the market
post-approval
because of drug induced liver injury
effects that occurred
after market approval.
And so this is the first data
where you have truth in animal in vivo,
truth in human in vivo,
and then, how did the chip perform?
It's the perfect data set to do so.
Yeah, we've developed something like 15
different organ chips.
We've done kidney, we've done intestine,
we've done the different parts of the
intestine,
the duodenum, ileum, jejunum, the colon.
We've done different parts of the lung,
the airway
and the air sac.
Lung on a chip, kidney on a chip, liver
on a chip,
A human mini brain on a chip, a gut on a
chip,
a human nerve on a chip.
Just think about whatever organ
and somebody is probably working on that
And they're actually being connected now
to create the human body on a chip.
This is like a huge area of research that
helps
to eliminate animal models.
Here we show an example of putting all
the tubing together
of different organs to essentially go
towards creating
that human body on a chip.
In southern California, the Terasaki
Institute is not only
developing organs on a chip,
they're 3D bioprinting entire organs.
Human organs.
No mouse brains, no monkey business.
One of the things that 3D bioprinting is,
is really applying 3D printing concepts
to biological
materials and tissues.
There's lots of different applications
that you could do
with this type of 3D bioprinter if you're
using it
to model disease.
If you want to, let's say make a cancer
model, you know,
you could print a pancreas, you could put
cancer cells
inside and then that would allow you to
have something
to test your drug therapies on instead of
an animal model.
So being able to build tissues in three
dimensions
and be able to use the cells of a, let's
say,
individual patient
and understand how that patient tissue
responds
to a particular drug is gonna be really
important.
The reason I got into this field is
really for replacing
body parts for variety of different
diseases.
Right now there is a huge demand for
organs that can be used
for treating people
and it's really the reason why we do a lot
of this 3D bioprinting and tissue
engineering.
It does sound a little bit like science
fiction,
the distant future, but this is now.
It's been now for quite some time.
And the government is slowly catching up.
The recent passage of the FDA
Modernization ACT now allows
these cutting edge, human-relevant
alternatives
to be considered by the FDA instead of
animal data
as long as they can compete with animal
models.
And remember, animal models are often
terrible.
The FDA now will consider those results in
lieu of animal models.
So that's absolutely changing.
These methods
were a dream some 50 years ago,
but over the last, uh, 20, 30 years, more
and more of them have been introduced.
Some 50 methods are now available
for which we have international consensus
that they're doing the trick.
We were funded to respond to COVID using
our lung chips.
We came up with drugs that moved
to clinical trials within months.
We have other ones, at least in our
models,
prevent infection not only by SARS-CoV-2,
but the original SARS CoV, MERS, multiple
types of influenza.
To actually do- enable drug discovery,
I think is gonna transform drug
development.
And Dr. Chandrasekera's own Canadian
Centre for Alternatives
to Animal Methods is helping
to lead the charge away from sacrificing
animals to the gods of science.
So my center has three main pillars.
We have a biomedical research pillar
where we develop,
validate, and promote animal free
technologies
for biomedical research
to understand human disease processes.
This is where we use these 3D bioprinted
tissue models
and we create insulin resistance in our
liver tissue model
and so much more.
We have a large number of research
projects looking at
how we develop disease, understanding
disease mechanisms,
and then also looking at drug toxicity.
We have a regulatory pillar where we work
with regulators like Health Canada to
modernize toxicology
and chemical safety testing in Canada.
And one of my favorite pillars is the
academic pillar.
This is where I'm developing cutting edge
academic programs
to train the next generation to think
outside the cage.
What the future of medicine is moving
towards is an era
of personalized medicine
and actually this is starting to happen
now.
People with diseases can have their
diseases
actually tested against different drugs
and vaccines.
So if I were to develop a breast cancer,
for example,
my biology, my tissues can be recreated
in these new
testing methods to screen for different
drugs
to see whether those drugs will be
effective against my
disease and will be safe in my biology.
That's the era of personalized medicine
we're heading towards.
Imagine this high throughput system where
you have
thousands of different patient avatars
where it's patient derived samples
and you could test so many drugs at the
same time
or like pick out the best ones
and choose that one to test on a patient
instead of waiting
to grow a disease in an animal model
and then waiting for them
to respond to the treatment or not.
It takes a long time, like, patient's
dying.
They need to know now like what, what can
be done?
I hadn't felt this sense of possibility
since the day
before I accidentally saw my therapist
had written "ugly
crier" on her notepad.
And yet, I had to ask,
because this all started with my
depression,
what could these new methods do for my
illness?
Obviously, mental health is one of the
things that is
huge in terms of our society and needing
to address it.
So there is a lot of opportunity to
actually not only
understand how the different
compounds affect the brain cells in a way
that either enhances
or reduces things that are associated
with anxiety
or depression, but also thinking about
how do we actually come up with new
solutions,
new treatments for this that doesn't
require compounds
or actually can synergize with other
things like being able
to have more relaxation time or other
things like that.
There's a lot of ways to actually come up
with models in a tissue
and then be able to test different
parameters in a way
that would be very difficult to do to a
human.
With these methods, science can advance
rapidly.
So maybe there is a world where I
genuinely feel better, one
where I go swimming instead of a rat
because I can actually get out of bed.
In some ways, the future is already here
because we have toxicity testing in the
21st century.
We have the ability to test hundreds
of chemicals all at once on many
different types of cells
and tissues, and then to put
that data together using machine learning
in order
to understand it.
We couldn't do that in the past.
Almost every company
and university involved in research could
make just
as much money if they were using
non-animal methods
as if they were using animals.
NIH could continue to dole out billions
of dollars in non-animal research grants
to universities
and they could continue to take that
overhead.
It's simply about trying to change minds,
trying
to build bridges, trying to advance new
methods
with greater funding of those methods.
We could do so much more.
We could come together as a community of
animal free
scientists and we can accelerate and
expand our programs.
Who's going to benefit at the end
of the day? It's the public.
It's anyone who's suffering from a disease
for which they've been waiting for an
effective treatment
for the last 20 years.
If we really put patients first, it
becomes really clear
that we need to move on from such outdated
animal-based technology.
The same way that we've moved forward
from using
horses for transportation.
We no longer rely on bulls to do
agriculture,
we have tractors. We use cell phones,
not pigeons. The same way.
We can't be stubborn
and insist that this is the gold standard
because it's far from being gold.
The future before us is in our hands.
If we as a society can put the time in to
build the laws
and the policies that will allow our
scientists
to develop these exciting new methods,
we're gonna be in a really good place
and we're gonna be seen as good ancestors.
But if we don't do that,
then we're gonna be stuck in the situation
where we have incomplete science and
incomplete answers.
We've seen companies
and regulatory agencies making
commitments to reduce
and replace tests on animals.
So it's not a question of "will" animal
testing end,
it's "when."
Right now, we're already there in terms
of getting rid of animal models.
So in cosmetics, for example,
in Europe, there's a huge push.
Any new cosmetic is not gonna have animal
models tested.
Once the political will is there, which
that requires everyday people.
When we have enough people who say that
we want
to end animal testing, that creates
momentum,
that gets law passed,
that gets non-animal testing methods
created and being implemented.
If you look at it just like one person,
you would think
that it's, it's not effective.
But together we are very effective.
Political will is a very effective way
of getting things done.
I decided it was time to hear from the
high priestess
of animal rights herself, Ingrid Newkirk.
I think any movement is just a collection
of people
and people shouldn't feel overwhelmed just
because they may not be working in a lab.
If they are, they should blow the whistle
on cruelty.
Um, but people don't have to dissect when
they're in school.
If they have medical training
that says you must use animals, they can
say no.
You know, we have a voice.
We can stand up for what we believe in.
We can never buy things that are tested
in animals' eyes
or down their throats, and we can go
and talk to our representatives and say,
enough is enough.
I want my money to go into modern
non-animal experiments,
not into the use of mice and monkeys and
dogs
and cats and so on.
Let's modernize medicine.
Just about the single most favorite
ethical principle across all cultures
is nonmaleficence: don't harm
innocent beings.
It is the most important ethical problem
that we face:
hurting other beings who are sentient but
innocent.
So instead of always trying to justify
breaking the principle of nonmaleficence
in our research,
why don't we try to do something
differently?
Well, I learned a lot. And my depression?
Gone. Zilch.
No more. After over a year of talking
to scientists about death and disease
and watching horrible footage from
laboratories,
I feel great. Jokes aside, oddly enough,
I do feel a lot of hope. Human beings,
for how ugly we can be
to ourselves and to others are also
capable
of profound creativity. When we're not
just using
that creativity for euphemisms designed
to avoid an ugly reality,
we can do amazing things, like when Dr.
Hartung developed a method
to replace a rabbit eye test some 30
years ago.
And our creativity can also mean
guaranteeing
that the next generation
of alternatives doesn't take 30 years
to go from being designed to actually
being implemented.
Alternatives to animal testing currently
receive only a
small fraction of the money that goes
into research
and look at what we've already gotten.
I think that, by default, most of us are
kind. A lot
of money rides on keeping us from seeing
the
ugly side of things.
I believe we only stop caring as a
consequence
of feeling powerless to help.
We owe it to ourselves
and to each other to make it easier to be
good,
and we can take better care of ourselves
so that less
of us need so much medicine in the first
place.
So whatever you take away from this
documentary,
I hope we can all agree on one thing:
The best way to help patients, scientists
traumatized by
what they believe they must do,
and the over 100 million animals used in
research
and testing each year is to rapidly fund
and promote these amazing alternatives
with more urgency than ever before.
The not so distant future could be
beautiful.
I hope I see you there.